Guide to the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Records, 1750-2014 and undated RL.10159
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Audiovisual, 1941-2011 and undated; 4; 2.8 Linear Feet 95 physical items
  - Down Home video recordings, 2002-2009 and undated; 5
    - Matzoh ball gumbo - Marcie Cohen Ferris, 2006 March 27; digital betacam, 2 of 3 (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Dbcam-002)
      Container label: "Matzoh Ball Gumbo overhead cameras"
    - Matzoh ball gumbo - Marcie Cohen Ferris, 2006 March 27; digital betacam, 3 of 3 (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Dbcam-003)
    - Down Home: Jewish life in North Carolina. Benefit dinner with Gov. James B. Hunt, N.C. Museum of History, 2007 January 11; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-005)
      Runtime 28 min.
    - Charlotte 6/13/07; part one rough cut 6/25, 2007 June; digital betacam (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Dbcam-007)
    - Peddler & mule, 2007 November 14; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-005)
    - Chanukah at Lerner School, 2007 December 4; digital betacam (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Dbcam-008)
    - Baby blessing - Patterson's Mill, 2008 February 19; digital betacam (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Dbcam-006)
    - Ed Cone - narration/southern acculturation points, etc., 2008 April 4; digital betacam (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Dbcam-004)
    - Seder - Will Grossman, 2008 April 4; digital betacam (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Dbcam-005)
    - Down home: Jewish life in North Carolina - Asheville Jewish Film Festival show copy, 2009 March 19; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-008)
      Runtime 83 min. 17 sec.
    - Down home: Jewish life in North Carolina (documentary film), 2009 November 19; digital betacam (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Dbcam-009)
      Master tape submitted to Atlanta Jewish Film Festival. Container label: "Down Home: Jewish Life in North Carolina, stereo audio - 16x9 widescreen (FHA) Master 2 of 2."
    - Down home: Jewish life in North Carolina (DVD release), 2009; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-004)
    - Down home: Jewish life in North Carolina - 4th and 8th grade films, 2011; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-019)
      A peddler's story: then and now (4th grade film); The North Carolina Jewish experience: an American immigration story (8th grade film)
    - Source tape, undated; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-013)
      Possibly footage for Down Home or another project.
    - Durham footage, undated; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-014)
    - Durham: a self portrait preview - Steven Channing/Video Dialogue Inc., circa 2008; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-031)
    - February one: the story of the Greensboro Four, 2003; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-002)
      Produced by Video Dialog Inc. Runtime approximately 60 min.
  - Documentaries and television programs, circa 1965-2005 and undated; 6
    The video recordings in this subseries include various documentaries and television programs related to Jews in the American South as well as other aspects of Jewish history and culture. Among the recordings are features on Rosenzweig Gallery exhibits and Duke University professor and JHFNC president Dr. Eric Meyers.
    - Creative Person, program "The World of Harry Golden", circa 1965-1966; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-011)
      Program produced by WGTV (University of Georgia) and National Educational Television.
    - Inside Duke - Cable 13, 1988 October 5; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-032)
      Duke University student production. Episode includes interview with Professors Carol Meyers and Eric Meyers.
    - North Carolina Now: Chanukiyahs at Rosenzweig Gallery (12/22/97), What we brought with us, NC Museum of History (12/30/97), 1997 December; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-026)
    - America's synagogue: a video portrait of Touro Synagogue, Newport, Rhode Island, 1998; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-011)
      Produced by the Society of Friends of Touro Synagogue. Runtime 12 min.
    - Delta Jews: Jews in the land of the blues, 1998; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-003)
      PBS documentary by Mike DeWitt. Narrated by Alfred Uhry. Runtime approximately 57 min.
    - The Jews of Memphis, 1999; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-012)
      Produced for the Jewish Historical Society of Memphis & the Mid-South, 1999. Based on the book "A biblical people in the Bible Belt: the Jewish community of Memphis, Tennessee, 1840-1950" by Selma S. Lewis. Runtime 58 min.
    - The Jews of Memphis, 1999, 2010; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-003)
      Produced for the Jewish Historical Society of Memphis & the Mid-South, 1999, 2010. Based on the book "A biblical people in the Bible Belt: the Jewish community of Memphis, Tennessee, 1840-1950" by Selma S. Lewis. Runtime 58 min.
    - Landmine Survivors' Network, 2000; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-035)
      Runtime 13 min. 25 sec.
    - They came for good: a history of Jews in the United States, 2001; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-004)
      [Part 1] Present at the Creation, 1654-1820. Produced by Amram Nowak Associates, 2001. Approximately 60 minutes.
    - They came for good: a history of Jews in the United States, 2001; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-028)
      [Part 2] Taking Root 1820-1880. Produced by Amram Nowak Associates, 2001. Approximately 60 minutes.
    - Land of promise: the Jews of South Carolina, 2002; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-023)
      Produced by Jewish Historical Society of South Carolina. Narrated by Blythe Danner. Runtime 57 min.
    - Push, pluck & perseverance: the story of Judaism in Charlotte (Charlotte Public Television), 2002; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-007)
    - Push, pluck & perseverance: the story of Judaism in Charlotte (Charlotte Public Television), 2002; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-018)
    - North Carolina People: Eric Meyers, Episode #3510, 2005 September 2; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-005)
    - At the altar of her memories, 2005; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-020)
      From container: "Through a mix of puppetry and story telling Bracha Ghilai, who spent her adolescent years in concentration camps, unlocks chapters from her painful past." Hebrew with English subtitles. Runtime 26 min. 53 sec.
    - Senator No (UNC-TV), 2007; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-021)
      Documentary film about NC Senator Jesse Helms by filmmaker John Wilson.
  - Other audiovisual material, 1941-2011 and undated; 7
    The video and sound recordings in this series are mainly unpublished recordings of religious services and other programming at North Carolina Jewish congregations. The series includes sound recordings of Rabbi Efraim Rosenzweig (Judea Reform Congregation), and other recordings related to Rosenzweig/JHFNC events and exhibits. Other materials in the subseries include home recordings acquired by the JHFNC from North Carolina Jewish families, including the Farber family of Weldon, NC, the Leder family of Wilson, NC, and the Shrago and Lacob families of Goldsboro and Fayetteville, NC.
    - Arthur Miller in Wilmington, 1941, BBC Radio 4, compact disc (Box 33, Audio-cd RL10159-CD-005)
      Runtime 28 min. 13 sec.
    - Menorah's little Seder (Menorah Records), 1951; phonodisc record, 45 rpm, 7 in, sides 1 and 2 (Box 35, Audio-phonodisc RL10159-PD-001)
      Written and told by Eve Lippman. Sung by Gladys Gewirtz and Moshe Leifman. Written on record sleeve: "Temple Beth-El, Lumberton, NC."
    - Menorah's little Seder (Menorah Records), 1951; phonodisc record, 45 rpm, 7 in, sides 3 and 4 (Box 35, Audio-phonodisc RL10159-PD-002)
    - Tell me about Chanukah [disc 1]: the story of Chanukah, 1951; phonodisc record, 7 in (Box 35, Audio-phonodisc RL10159-PD-003)
      Script and production by Helen Stambler, songs by Victoria Yousha, music by Elaine Wertheim, narrated by Edward Gold. Record set is from Temple Beth-El, Lumberton, NC.
    - Tell me about Chanukah [disc 2]: Chanukah melodies (New York: Ktav Publishing House), 1951; phonodisc record, 7 in (Box 35, Audio-phonodisc RL10159-PD-004)
      Script and production by Helen Stambler, songs by Victoria Yousha, music by Elaine Wertheim, narrated by Honore Singer. Record set is from Temple Beth-El, Lumberton,
    - Yom Kippur service by Rabbi H.A. Friedman and Cantor J. Rosenstein made on Oct. 4, 1954, Statesville, NC, 1954 October 4; compact disc (Box 33, Audio-cd RL10159-CD-001)
      Copy of a broadcast on WISC radio. Runtime 15 min. 10 sec.
    - Israel songs for children in Hebrew by Miriam Ben-Ezra; accompaniment Eli Plotnick (New York: Folkways Records), 1958; phonodisc record, 33 1/2 rpm, 10 in (Box 35, Audio-phonodisc RL10159-PD-005)
      Folkways catalog number FC7226. The LP jacket is lacking the descriptive notes. Record set is from Temple Beth-El, Lumberton, NC.
    - Ellis Farber - 80th birthday celebration, 1985 December 8; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-009)
      Home video presumably filmed in Weldon, NC. Runtime approximately 14 min.
    - Manu's wedding, 1988; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-021)
      Wedding of Debbie Crovitz, March 1988, at Hotel Europa, Chapel Hill, NC. Officiated by Rabbi Efraim Rosenzweig (Judea Reform Congregation, Durham, NC).
    - Mona Lisa of the Galilee, Sepphoris excavation, 1989; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-014)
    - Efraim Rosenzweig - poetry reading, 1991 May; audiocassette (Box 34, Audio-cassette RL10159-CS-005)
      Reading of his poetry by Efraim M. Rosenzweig.
    - Efraim Rosenweig - exhibit listing, 1991 November 24; audiocassette (Box 34, Audio-cassette RL10159-CS-002)
      Recording of Rosenzweig describing artifacts for the Efraim and Marian Rosenzweig Judaica and Hebraica Exhibit at the Judea Reform Congregation.
    - Efraim Rosenzweig - general talk and sermon, circa 1991; audiocassette (Box 34, Audio-cassette RL10159-CS-001)
      Sermon given by Efraim M. Rosenzweig at the Judea Reform Congregation.
    - Museum opening - Efraim and Marian Rosenzweig Judaica and Hebraica Exhibit at the Judea Reform Congregation, Durham, NC, 1992 June 7; audiocassette (Box 34, Audio-cassette RL10159-CS-004)
    - A tour of the Judaica Gallery with Dr. Abram Kanof, 1992; compact disc (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-CD-003)
      Produced by Elizabeth Holloway, North Carolina Museum of Art. Runtime 00:42:43.
    - Travelling shoes, 1994 December 31; compact disc (Box 33, Audio-cd RL10159-CD-002)
      Presented by Southern Cultures, mastered by UNC Southern Folklife Colletion. Runtime 79 min. 14 sec.
    - Jewish/Arab extracultural encounters, 1995 November 5; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-025)
    - Celebrating 100 Years: Temple Israel, Charlotte, North Carolina, 1895-1995, betacam-sp (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-Bcam-004)
      Produced by Eneman Media
    - Celebrating 100 Years: Temple Israel, Charlotte, North Carolina, 1895-1995, VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-017)
    - What we brought with us: mementos of the flight from Europe, 1933-1950 - public reception, Duke University Perkins Library, 1996 October 13; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-020)
    - Holy transmitters: portraits of the Mekubalim (Jewish Mystics) reception - artist B.J. Goldberg, 1997 April 20; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-001)
      Museum of the Jewish Family public reception at Lilly Library, Duke University.
    - Meaning of light in Jewish tradition, Chapel Hill Town Hall public reception, 1997 February 9; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-015)
    - Temple Emanuel at the millenium: 90 years of faith, courage, and vision, circa 1997-2000; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-024)
      Narrated by Nat Labell. Runtime approximately 16 min.
    - Leder family history, 1997, 2003; computer optical disc
      Disc two: Leder family history as told by Fanny [Fannie] Bernstein. Interviewed by Arnold and Steven Leder, 1/12/97. 1 video transferred from VHS. Modified 2003-12-31. Runtime 00:31:32
    - Stephen Smith talk and reception, 1998 January 11; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-013)
    - The Running Stag - Reception and Exhibition, 1998 May 10; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-030)
    - North Carolina Israel Chorale, 2000 July 1; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-016)
    - Tape 1 Stamp CU's No Audio, 2000 July 2?; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-010)
      Presumably related to "The Running Stag" exhibit.
    - Museum Stamp Exhibit, Mr. Hertz Interview #2, 2000 July 26; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-009)
    - Tape 3 Interviews (Sound) Stamp CU's, 2000 July 2?; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-011)
    - [Bert Chessin], 2001 May 9; digital audio tape (Box 34, Audio-cassette RL10159-DAT-001)
      Audio recording of klezmer musician Bert Chessin.
    - Migrations exhibit - East Carolina University, 2001 October 7; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-022)
      introduction, speakers including Leonard Rogoff, Q&A panel. Footage of exhibit. Runtime approximately 113 min.
    - Migrations: Jews in Eastern North Carolina - exhibit footage, circa 2001; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-010)
      Footage of Migrations exhibit displays at unknown location with music (no other audio).
    - American Hebrew Academy, [2003]; VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL10159-VHS-019)
      Promotional video about the American Hebrew Academy in Greensboro, NC. Runtime approximately 15 min.
    - American Hebrew Academy, 2003; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-013)
    - International Civil Rights Center and Museum walkthrough, 2003; compact disc (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-CD-004)
      Computer-simulated model of the International Civil Rights Center & Museum (Greensboro, NC). No audio.
    - Jewish Federation of Chapel Hill and Durham: 30 year gala, 2004
    - Joyce Antler - Passing the "Torch of Idealism": Gertrude Weil as Southern Jewish Citizen-Activist, 2006 March 21; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-015)
      Paper presented at the Carolina Center for Jewish Studies, March 21, 2006. Videotaped by Sheldon T. Becker. Runtime 72 min. 36 sec.
    - NC Hillel: 70 Years, 2006 November 4; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-007)
      Runtime 6 min. 46 sec.
    - Loyalty to a tradition: the Fleishman family in America, 2006; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-002)
      Runtime 27 min. 44 sec.
    - Temple Emanuel (Winston-Salem) 75th Anniversary, 2007
    - A loving interview between Grandfather (Alywn D. Goldstein) and Grandson (Keith Greenspon) (Charlotte, NC Story Corps recording), 2008 February 8; compact disc (Box 33, Audio-cd RL10159-CD-006)
      The interview is part of the Lowcountry Digital Library, College of Charleston. Runtime 42 min. 31 sec.
    - Banners Worship, 2008 August 24; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-004)
      Possibly related to the Harvest Fellowship Church, Goldsboro, NC.
    - Jewish banners (12 tribes) at Harvest Fellowship Church, 2008 August 24?; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-012)
    - Power In the Word Progam, Believer's Auth. #50, Changing Your Thinking, Dr. Pete Norris, edited by Ben Rice, 2008 September 11; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-006)
    - Temple Beth El (Durham, NC), - Yom Kippur service, 2009 September 30; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-014)
      Runtime 111 min. 9 sec.
    - Leder family history, disc 1, 2008; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-001)
      Leder family history as told by Morris Leder; Baker family history as told by Minnie Lee Baker Leder. Transferred from VHS.
    - Leder family history, disc 2, [2008]; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-022)
      Leder family history as told by Fanny [Fannie] Bernstein. Transferred from VHS. Possibly a duplicate of 2003 transfer.
    - Bandana Klezmer: Eastern European Jewish celebration music, circa 2008; compact disc (Box 33, Audio-cd RL10159-CD-007)
      Runtime 26 min. 49 sec.
    - Temple Beth Or (Raleigh, NC) - Chanukkah service, 2009 December 28; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-009)
      Audio only.
    - Temple of Israel: a new beginning, 2011 October 18; DVD (Box 33, Video-disc RL10159-DVD-016)
      History and renovation of Temple of Israel in Wilmington, NC. Features Beverly Tetterton.
    - 3D Stuff, undated; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-001)
    - [Untitled], undated; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-002)
      Unknown contents. Possibly footage for Down Home or another project.
    - [Untitled], undated; mini-dv (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-003)
    - Dinner Jewish project, undated; mini-dv, 1 of 2 (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-007)
      Container label: "Dinner Jewish Project 1"
    - Dinner Jewish project, undated; mini-dv, 2 of 2 (Box 34, Video-cassette RL10159-MDV-008)
      Container label: "Jewish Film Dinner 2, Rex Miller"
    - [Lacob/Shrago family], undated; audiocassette, 1 of 2 (Box 34, Audio-cassette RL10159-CS-006)
      Container label: "Mr. Lacob; Kadish - Gertrude Lacob; Bar mitzvah - maftir - Mr. Lacob singing; Mark/Bill talking about family"
    - [Lacob/Shrago family], undated; audiocassette, 2 of 2 (Box 34, Audio-cassette RL10159-CS-007)
      Container label: "Hyman talks to Philip Lacob"
    - [Torah service, unidentified cantor], undated; audiocassette (Box 34, Audio-cassette RL10159-CS-003)
      Torah service, unidentified cantor